Adee Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Adee Family Papers 1824-1966
MSS10231
Adee family
300 items
3 containers
1.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journals, correspondence, poetry, speeches and writings, newspaper clippings, genealogical records of the Adee and Graham families, and miscellaneous family material, including papers of Alvey A. Adee, chief of the Diplomatic Bureau at the United States Department of State and assistant secretary of state; Augustus Alvey Adee, United States Navy surgeon; and David Graham Adee, author and lawyer.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adee family.; Adee, Alvey A. (Alvey Augustus), 1842-1924. Alvey A. Adee papers.; Adee, Amelia Kinnaird Graham, 1812-1864.; Adee, Augustus Alvey, 1802-1844. Augustus Alvey Adee papers.; Adee, David Graham, 1837-1901. David Graham Adee papers.; Adee, Lucy A. K. (Lucy Amelia Kinnaird), 1812-1864.; Graham family.; Hartsuff, Albert, 1837-1908.; Hartsuff, George Lucas, 1830-1874.; Hunsberger, George S., 1914- George S. Hunsberger papers.; Stansbury family.; Vitte, S. I︠U︡. (Sergeĭ I︠U︡lʹevich), graf, 1849-1915. Graf Sergeĭ I︠U︡lʹevich Vitte letter. 1893.
Organizations
Potomac (Frigate); United States. Army--Officers.; United States. Army--Surgeons.; United States. Department of State.; United States. Navy--Cruise, 1835-1837.; United States. Navy--Cruise, 1840-1841.; United States. Navy--Surgeons.; Vincennes (Sloop of war)
Subjects
Book collecting.; Poetry.; Scottish Americans.; Shells.
Places
China--History--Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901.; Europe--Description and travel.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Provenance
The papers of the Adee family were given to the Library of Congress by the District of Columbia Public Library in 1925, with additions received from Carroll Stansbury, Joan Carroll Stansbury, and George S. Hunsberger in 1965-1984 and a transfer from the Library of Congress Preservation Microfilming Office in 1979. A journal of Augustus Alvey Adee covering the years 1835-1836 was purchased in 2011.
Transfers
Photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Adee Family Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of the Adee family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the Adee family span the years 1824-1966 and consist of awards, catalogs, correspondence, journals, a medical degree, newspaper clippings, poetry, speeches, and writings. The papers are chiefly those of Augustus Alvey Adee (1802-1844), United States Navy surgeon, and his sons David Graham Adee (1837-1901), author and lawyer, and Alvey A. Adee (1842-1924), assistant secretary of state and chief of the Diplomatic Bureau, Department of State.
Material of Augustus Alvey Adee includes correspondence to his wife, Amelia Kinnaird (Graham) Adee, written primarily while he was serving as fleet surgeon on the Potomac (frigate) along the coast of South America, 1840-1841; journals while he was a surgeon on the Vincennes (Sloop of war) during a cruise in the Pacific, 1835-1838; notes on the Adee family of Scotland; marriage and baptism records of the Adee and Graham families; and catalogs of Adee's book and seashell collections.
The David Graham Adee material consists mostly of published writings and poetry and also includes material relating to the Civil War service of Major General George Lucas Hartsuff and his brother, Albert Hartsuff, assistant surgeon in the Union army.
Papers of Alvey A. Adee include correspondence and newspaper clippings concerning his diplomatic career, a journal of an extensive bicycling trip he made throughout Europe in 1867, and manuscript copies of his writings and poetry. Also in the collection are a book of poems and notes on the Adee and Stansbury families by Lucy A. K. Adee and a master's thesis written by George S. Hunsberger on the diplomatic career of Alvey A. Adee, with references to the Boxer Rebellion.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by name of person.
Container List
- Adee, Augustus Alvey (Box 1)
  - Catalog of seashells and journal, 1825, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1831-1834, 1840-1841, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Journal, 1835-1838, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Miscellany, 1824, undated (Box 1)
- Adee, Alvey A. (Box 1)
  - Catalog of books, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864-1867, 1877, 1886, 1893, 1906-1922, undated (Box 2)
  - Journal, 1867 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1870, 1888, undated (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1898-1924, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - Speech, 1912 (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1856-1857, 1867-1872, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Adee, David Graham (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1894 (Box 2)
  - Writings (Box 3)
    - 1856, 1862-1872, 1880-1881, 1891-1894 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Adee, Lucy A. K. (Box 3)
  - Miscellany, 1953, 1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Writings, 1957 (Box 3)
- Hunsberger, George S., 1953, (2 folders) (Box 3)